Bachhofer, Ludwig; Papers ger018
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Ludwig Bachhofer Papers
1922-1968
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Bachhofer, Ludwig, b. 1894
ger018
12.18 cubic ft.
This collection contains correspondence and materials related to Ludwig Bachhofer's professional interests in and knowledge about Asian art.
Biographical History
Ludwig Bachhofer was born in Munich, Germany on June 30, 1894, the son of Adolf and Paula (Hartmann). He was a student at Gymnasium Realgymnasium, Munich from 1905 to 1914. He received his doctoral degree from the University of Munich in 1921.
From 1921 to 1923, Bachhofer was an assistant in the Ethnographisches Museum, Munich. From 1926 to 1934, he was privatdozent, History of Asian Art, at the University of Munich.
He came to the United States in 1935 and was appointed professor of history of Asian art at the University of Chicago, where he remained until 1965.
Bachhofer married Hilda Nelson on November 24, 1926. He passed away in 1976, survived by his wife and daughter Else.
Scope and Contents
The Ludwig Bachhofer Papers consist of correspondence in German and English with Henry Bergsen and others about Asian art; research notes, manuscripts, and articles; and photographs of art works and of the University of Munich after the 1944 bombing. The major portion of the collection is comprised of photographs, picture postcards, color plates and reproductions (ca. 2440) assembled by Bachhofer during the course of his career.
The University Libraries also has Bachhofer's library (including many annotated books) relating to Chinese, Japanese, and Indian art history.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series.
Acquisition Information
1978 The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections received the bulk of this collection from Mrs. Ludwig (Hilda) Bachhofer.
2005 Granddaughter Helga Sinaiko donated additional correspondence.
2011 Greatgrangdaughter Eve Sinaiko donated addition correspondence, sketches and books.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Art; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Art -- History; Art, Asian; Correspondence; Photographs; Bachhofer, Ludwig, b. 1894; Bergsen, Henry; University of Chicago; Universitt Mnchen
- Correspondence with Henry Bergsen, 1931-1936 (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 1)
- Notes, found in Henry Bergsen correspondence, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1930-1962 (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 3)
- "Chinese Art.-!", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 4)
- "Chinese Art Treasures", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 5)
- "Einf0hrung in die Kunst Ostasiens," Notes, 1922 (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 6)
- "Evolution of Perceptual Imagination", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 7)
- "Evolution of Presentations in Painting and Sculpture", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 8)
- "Hsio-Yen Suim. On Ming Dynasty Book Illustration", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 9)
- "Notizen zur Zentralasien", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 10)
- "Osvald Siren: Histoire de la Peinture Chinoise", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 11)
- "Representation of man, Greek, geometric", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 12)
- "The Representation of Space in Chinese Painting During the First Thousand Years of the Christian Era", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 13)
- "Some principal remarks on Tang and Sung Ceramics", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 14)
- "Victor Lowenfeld: The Nature of Creative Activity. New York 1939", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 15)
- "Vom. kutinstlerischen in der Kunst. Ein Zwiegesprach zwischen Musiker und Maler", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 16)
- "Works of art express the ideas and ideals ...", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 17)
- "Zum. Stimmungsgehalt durch den Landskapen", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 18)
- "ZurTheorie der Bildenden Kunst", Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 19)
- Chinese and Greek art, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 20)
- Chinese painting and poetry, 1953 (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 21)
- Critiques: 2 Manuscripts, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 22)
- Hinduisierung, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 23)
- Japanese art, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 24)
- Japanese woodworking, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 25)
- Kunstgeschichte, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 26)
- Notes, untitled manuscripts, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous note slips pertaining to: "Altgermanische Ornament," "Irant" "Volkerwanderung," "Sarmaten," etc., Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 28)
- Notes by Bachhofer on various articles, books, etc. read, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 29)
- Miscellaneous working notes, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 30)
- Offprints by Bachhofer, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 31)
- Contracts, 2 miscellaneous documents, Notes, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 32)
- Soper, Alexander, offprints, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 33)
- The Del Drago Collection of Chinese Painting. Inventory. Also notes on selections by Bachhofer, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 34)
- Clippings on various topics, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 35)
- Student papers, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 36)
- Unidentified photographs, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 37)
- Abhayagiri Dagaba Auuradhapura, Ceylon, South shrine. Photograhs of carvings, Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 38)
- Amaravati (India). Sculpture, carvings. Photographs and picture postcards (1 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 39)
- Amaravati (India). Sculpture, carvings. Photographs and picture postcards (2 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 40)
- Amaravati (India). Sculpture, carvings. Photographs and picture postcards (3 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 41)
- Amaravati (India). Sculpture, carvings. Photographs and picture postcards (4 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 42)
- Barhut Photographs (1 of 3), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 43)
- Barhut Photographs (2 of 3), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 44)
- Barhut Photographs (3 of 3), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 45)
- Budh Gaya Photographs (1 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 46)
- Budh Gaya Photographs (2 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 47)
- Budh Gaya Photographs (3 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 48)
- Budh Gaya Photographs (4 of 4), Undated (Box 1 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 49)
- Chinese Art Treasures. Photo reproductions of objects in exhibit reviewed by Bachhofer for Pantheon. Munich, 1962 (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 1)
- Chinese bronzes, photos, reproductions, postcards, etc. (1 of 6), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 2)
- Chinese bronzes, photos, reproductions, postcards, etc. (2 of 6), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 3)
- Chinese bronzes, photos, reproductions, postcards, etc. (3 of 6), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 4)
- Chinese bronzes, photos, reproductions, postcards, etc. (4 of 6), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 5)
- Chinese bronzes, photos, reproductions, postcards, etc. (5 of 6), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 6)
- Chinese bronzes, photos, reproductions, postcards, etc. (6 of 6), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 7)
- Chinese ceramics, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 8)
- Chinese painting, photographs, reproductions, picture postcards (1 of 3), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 9)
- Chinese painting, photographs, reproductions, picture postcards (2 of 3), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 10)
- Chinese painting, photographs, reproductions, picture postcards (3 of 3), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 11)
- "Chinesische und Japanische Malerei vom 10. bis 18. Jh," Munich, Ludwig Bachhofer advisor, 1930 March (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 12)
- Clicki Goloubew, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 13)
- Del Drago Collection. Photographs from the collection, arranged by catalog sequence, some duplicates (1 of 3), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 14)
- Del Drago Collection. Photographs from the collection, arranged by catalog sequence, some duplicates (2 of 3), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 15)
- Del Drago Collection. Photographs from the collection, arranged by catalog sequence, some duplicates (3 of 3), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 16)
- Florence museum (Italy), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 17)
- Gandhara, photographs (1 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 18)
- Gandhara, photographs (2 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 19)
- Gandhara, photographs (3 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 20)
- Gandhara, photographs (4 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 21)
- Gupta, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 22)
- India, photographs of statues, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 23)
- Japanese ceramics, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 24)
- Japanese painting, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 25)
- Mathura, Photographs (1 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 26)
- Mathura, Photographs (2 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 27)
- Mathura, Photographs (3 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 28)
- Mathura, Photographs (4 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 29)
- Mavrya und verschiedenes, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 30)
- Munich architecture (churches, castles), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 31)
- Neolithic sites in Northern China, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 32)
- Oster Insel (Easter Island), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 33)
- 19. Persian art. 9 postcards., Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 34)
- Persian miniaturep, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 35)
- Sanchi, photographs (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 36)
- Sanchi, photographs (2 of 2), Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 37)
- Statuary: Porcelain, pottery, bronze, iron, Undated (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 38)
- University of Munich after bombing of July 13, 1944 (Box 2 (Ludwig Bachhofer Papers ), Folder 39)